So, hello.
I'm an independent artist,
writer, and coder based in the UK.
“FreeThem” is a narrative game web app
that I'm creating using HTML, CSS,
and JavaScript.
It offers or implies a feminist critique
of menstrual tracking apps
and how they shape diverse users’
understandings of their bodies.
This creative work is an output from
an international research project, “The
Intimate Technology Shaping
Millions of Lives,” led by Sarah Riley,
professor of critical health psychology
at Massey University in New Zealand.
And the members of the research team
are on the screen.
Millions of people worldwide use digital
apps to monitor their menstrual cycles.
These apps can be experienced
as empowering, but they're not neutral.
They play a role in how users understand
their bodies and by extension,
their selves, their relationships,
and their place in the world.
Importantly, menstrual tracking apps
are designed around a prototypical user:
a white, affluent, cisgender,
heterosexual, able-bodied young woman,
which reinforces narrow, potentially
harmful ideas about normal or ideal
bodies.
The research project asks,
“What are the experience of experiences
of the many non-prototypical users
whose bodies, identities, or life stages
are marginalized by these apps?” So,
because “menstrual tracking
app” is quite a mouthful,
I'll use MTA for short from now on.
So the research team conducted
participatory research
with MTA users in New Zealand.
They focused on three life stage cohorts:
16-to-18-year-olds,
postnatal, and perimenopausal groups.
They were particularly interested
in talking to people who are less
likely to be represented in research,
including indigenous
Māori and takatāpui people—
Excuse my pronunciation.
People managing chronic health
conditions or disability.
People identifying as fat or experiencing
weight stigma, and
or who are gender or sexually diverse.
The findings give unprecedented insight
into how MTAs shape diverse users
experiences of their bodies,
and they are generating ideas
on how these apps might be designed
to be affirmative and inclusive.
Another important output of the research
is the story game web app
that I'm creating.
It's for mobile first,
but all screen sizes eventually.
And here on-screen is my creative brief.
So “FreeThem” is a creative expression
of the research findings.
Research with the postnatal
and perimenopausal groups
went ahead as planned,
but the teenage cohort
has taken much longer
and the data isn't ready yet.
So initially, I was asked to create a
story driven app focusing on postnatal and
menopausal users of MTAs.
However, the team are keen to include
16-to-18-year-olds, so subject to funding,
I'll be incorporating those stories
at a later date.
So some of the main themes
from the research in those
in the postnatal and perimenopausal groups
are the apps are paradoxical.
There's a tension between care
versus control.
There are— the apps are experienced
as empowering, but at the same time,
non-prototypical users
experience exclusions and misfitting.
And the apps can exacerbate
existing inequities that reinforce
stigmatizing norms
and the pressure to regulate oneself.
The apps also reinforce
the reproductive centered
biomedical paradigm
by prioritizing fertility and pregnancy.
There's an implicit sense
of perimenopausal “crones” versus
celebrated mothers.
And there's a big issue around trust
and de-trust of both apps
and medical authority.
For example, a frequent complaint through
the research is of doctors not listening,
so users need the apps as an advocacy tool
to collect data to track symptoms,
as well as to do things like get pregnant.
But they're also aware that they can't
necessarily trust these commercial apps
with their private data,
which can be exploited in so many ways.
Also, health is hard
work, and MTAs tend to add to this burden.
So I'm of a generation
that didn't have access to MTAs.
I've never used one,
so I researched a variety of apps, MTAs,
and tried them by entering fake data, etc.
and what struck me is the vast majority
look remarkably similar.
Pinks and
pastel colors really dominate.
They also have a predilection
for representing
app users in this flat cartoon style.
There seems to be an attempt
to represent diverse users
and body types,
but the cartoon style style
is homogenizing and erases
bodily human imperfections.
So I wanted to emulate
this kind of aesthetics.
I wanted to design a story game app
that initially and superficially resembles
a menstrual tracking app
to lure the player in.
So the characters for this on-screen
now is my app.
The characters are fictional, but they're
based on the research participants.
Each character is a few participants,
kind of blended together
that kind of composites.
As they currently stand,
there are three postnatal characters:
Lucy, Danny, and Finley,
who is non-binary; and three
perimenopausal characters:
Arona—who is Maori—Zoe, and Claire.
Each character has an
associated casual game,
whose procedural rhetoric expresses
some of the frustrations
of using menstrual tracking apps.
Some games are based on overt
or explicit features of typical MTAs:
period logging,
identifying the symptoms of PMS
or perimenopause,
predicting facility type cycles.
Other games speak to more hidden
or covert characteristics.
As I said, using MTAs is hard work,
adding to the pressures of daily life
at companies that sell or abuse users’
private data.
The app encourages you to play the games.
It has a particular voice, which
I think of as another distinct character,
and privately
I characterize that as the “MTA Wizard,”
and I'm still working on that aspect
because it actually is a work in progress.
The app tries to distract you
from the characters’ stories.
It wants you to play the games
much in the same way that commercial apps
want to capture user's attention,
but the women
and the non-binary person
want to communicate their experiences.
They want you to listen to them.
So as you play and
learn more about the fictional characters,
the aesthetic changes.
The representation of the individuals
becomes more rounded,
not necessarily more realistic,
but they become more visually rounded
as the characters become more rounded.
In narrative terms,
as you, the player, learn more about them
and their experiences.
The point is that as you listen to what
the women and non-binary person
have to say, they can begin to escape
or emerge from the prism
of flat caricature.
So I want to play some video
recordings of the app
in this mobile device format.
So the first panel that you can see is
takes you through the player
experience of the Lucy game story.
Lucy is a postnatal character.
It is possible
to win the game,
but not in that particular iteration.
So here's Lucy's story
and will be scrolling quickly
through it in a moment.
But here's the app
trying to get you to go back to the game.
So as you read through Lucy's story,
you've come to the end
where you you can free her,
you can set Lucy free,
and then she encourages you to go
and help the others in the app.
So I'll just play you some of the other
characters’ games,
just briefly, just to give you an idea.
So Arona is— Ooh, sorry.
Arona is a perimenopausal,
and Zoe is also perimenopausal.
So some of the games are winnable
and some aren't.
So here we have Finley, who's postnatal,
Claire is perimenopausal,
and Danny is postnatal.
So there will be a global game
scoring system
that will track how many games
you've kind of won or lose— are lost.
I haven't yet implemented that,
but basically that's not the real point.
That's a distraction.
The important thing is listening
to the people, listening
to the characters.
So when you've freed
all the characters,
you get to the ending where the characters
collectively express what they want
and how they envisage—
what possibilities they envisage
for these technologies in the future
and the wider health and social setting.
So that's where the project is at at
the moment.
I will be
putting online a private beta testing
version early next month.
So if you'd like to— That's basically
for the research team and participants.
But if you'd like to take part
and give us some feedback, I'd be very—
I'd like that a lot.
So I'll put my
email in the chat.
If you'd like to.
And I'll send you the link.
And then you'll be able
to test the app as well.
Thank you.